Guide to the Theodore Rockwell Papers 1915-2013
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center
Theodore Rockwell Papers
1915-2013
1940-2010
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center Special Collections & University Archives Research Center 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2075 Email: scarc@oregonstate.edu Web: http://scarc.library.oregonstate.edu
MSS Rockwell
Rockwell, Theodore.
28 cubic feet, including 85 photographs, 7 microfiche, and 5 audiocassette tapes; 8 gigabytes of digital files including 615 digital images; 2 5.25" floppy disks; 16 3.5" floppy disks 85 boxes, including 1 oversize box
The Theodore Rockwell Papers document the life and career of Ted Rockwell, a member of the Manhattan Project, technical director for the U.S. Navy's nuclear propulsion initiative under Admiral H. G. Rickover, and co-founder of engineering firm MPR Associates, Inc. and nuclear advocacy group Radiation, Science, and Health, Inc. The collection includes correspondence, publications, research files, administrative documents, and memorabilia from his career. The collection also documents Rockwell's interest in parapsychology and includes extensive research materials on consciousness studies, telekinesis, dowsing, extraterrestrials, and other phenomena.
Biographical Note:
Theodore Rockwell was an engineer deeply involved in the genesis of atomic energy through his participation in the Manhattan Project at Oak Ridge and, later, the development of the United States' nuclear-powered naval fleet. He co-founded MPR Associates, Inc., an engineering firm, and served as vice president of Radiation, Science, and Health, Inc., a not-for-profit special interest group supporting the development and adoption of nuclear energy as a power source. He was widely recognized as an authority on nuclear power, a prominent pro-nuclear activist, a respected biographer of Admiral Hyman Rickover, and an active member of the international parapsychology community.
Rockwell was born in Chicago in 1922 and raised in Winnetka, Illinois where he attended New Trier High School. In 1939, he entered the chemical engineering program at Princeton University. He received his bachelor's degree in 1943 and his master's in 1944. Beginning in 1943, Rockwell worked as a process improvement engineer in the Electromagnetic Separation Pilot Plant at Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL). Later, he was promoted to head of Radiation Shielding Engineering. In December 1945, the Saturday Evening Post published an article by Rockwell entitled "Frontier Life Among the Atom Splitters," one of the first accounts of work on the Manhattan Project at Oak Ridge. Rockwell wedded his wife, Mary, at Oak Ridge in 1946.
In 1949, Rockwell left ORNL to begin work at the U.S. Naval Reactors Headquarters where he worked with the U.S. Navy and the Atomic Energy Commission to develop the world's first nuclear-powered fleet. In 1953, he became director of the Navy's Nuclear Technology Division where he oversaw the design of cooling and shielding systems for reactors. In 1955, he was named Technical Director of the Navy's nuclear program and reported directly to Admiral Hyman Rickover. Rockwell was instrumental in the design and construction of numerous historically significant vessels including the USS Nautilus, the USS Enterprise, and the USS Long Beach. In the course of his work with the Navy, Rockwell edited several important offerings in nuclear reactor design including The Reactor Shielding Design Manual and The Shippingport Pressurized Water Reactor, participated in nuclear submarine and aircraft carrier sea trials, and observed the detonation of a nuclear weapon at the Nevada Test Site.
In 1964, Rockwell co-founded MPR Associates, Inc. with fellow Navy Reactors alums Harry Mandil and Robert Panoff. The firm helped the U.S. Navy design a maintenance program for its nuclear submarine fleet, designed and tested components of the Loss-of-Fluid Test (LOFT) reactor facility at the Idaho National Engineering Laboratory, and conducted operations on post-meltdown Three Mile Island Reactor Two. During this time, Rockwell was also a research associate for the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies, Chairman of the Atomic Industrial Forum’s Reactors Safety Task Force, and Consultant to the Joint Congressional Committee on Atomic Energy. He retired from MPR in 1987 but continued in an active role in the company until his death. In 1996, James Muckerheide and Ted Rockwell co-founded Radiation, Science, and Health, Inc as president and vice president respectively. RSH was conceived as a direct response to the anti-nuclear movement and intended to influence regulatory reform within the nuclear power industry. Among RSH's activities was a 2000-2003 legal challenge to the Environmental Protection Agency's regulation of radionuclides in drinking water.
In addition to his long career in nuclear science and engineering, Rockwell was also a successful author. He published The Rickover Effect (a biography of Admiral Rickover), Creating the New World (an autobiographical history of early nuclear engineering), The Virtual Librarian (a futuristic mystery novel) and Vice Versa (a triology of plays), as well as numerous scientific and popular articles. Rockwell also cultivated an interest in the field of parapsychology, loosely defined as the study of paranormal phenomena including but not limited to extrasensory perception, psychokinesis, and psychic healing. Rockwell was an avid participant in the parapsychology community and maintained membership in numerous related organizations, published widely within the field, and even conducted research into psychokinesis.
Rockwell was the recipient of numerous awards and honors during his lifetime including the first American Nuclear Society Lifetime Achievement Award (1986), a Distinguished Service Medal from the U.S. Navy and the Atomic Energy Commission (1964), an honorary doctorate from Tri-State College (1960), and the Edward Teller Award (2006), and also held several patents in the field of nuclear engineering. Rockwell passed away on March 31, 2013.
The Theodore Rockwell Papers are comprised of materials representing the career and personal interests of nuclear engineer, author, biographer, and parapsychology researcher Ted Rockwell. The collection includes personal and professional correspondence, extensive subject files, lecture and speech materials, engineering design documents, professional literature, biographical data, organizational administrative materials, photographs, and memorabilia documenting Rockwell's career in the field of nuclear engineering. These materials represent his work at Oak Ridge National Laboratories during and after the Manhattan Project, his role as Technical Director of the U.S. Navy's nuclear propulsion initiative, his work as co-founder and director of the engineering firm MPR Associates, Inc., and his service as Vice President of Radiation, Science, and Health, Inc.
Also included is an extensive body of material in the field of parapsychology including literature from scores of research and education organizations, articles, clippings, correspondence, and publications. Topics include psychokinesis, extrasensory perception, faith healing, and extraterrestrial life. The collection also represents significant organizations and individuals within the parapsychology community including the Parapsychological Association and the American Society of Dowsers, James Randi, Anne Gehman, and Bruce and John Klingbeil.
A record of Rockwell's extensive publishing history is also present within the collection and includes documents from his work on The Rickover Effect (a biography of Admiral Rickover), Creating the New World (an autobiographical history of early nuclear engineering), and The Virtual Librarian (a futuristic mystery novel), as well as numerous technical and popular articles in the fields of nuclear engineering, radiation health and safety, nuclear power, and parapsychology.
The Theodore Rockwell Papers are arranged into eight series: I. Correspondence, 1966-2011; II. Biographical Materials, 1931-2010; III. Early Development of Nuclear Energy, 1940-2011; IV. U.S. Navy, 1949-2012; V. MPR Associates, Inc., 1963-2013; VI. Radiation, Science, and Health, Inc., 1981-2009; VII. Nuclear Power, 1915-2013; VIII. Parapsychology, 1924-2011; and IX. Electronic Recrods, 1945-2013.
Health records in Series VII, confidential records in Series IX, and unprocessed electronic records contained in this collection are restricted. All other materials are open for research.
Electronic records may be accessed via the electronic records kiosk in the Special Collections & Archives Research Center Reading Room. File formats include Microsoft Word (doc), Rich Text Format (rtf), Portable Document Format (pdf), HTML (htm and html), JPEG (jpg), MP4 (mp4), and video object (vob), information (ifo), and backup (bup) files.
The Theodore Rockwell Papers were donated to the OSU Libraries Special Collections & Archives Research Center by the Rockwell estate in 2013.
Related Materials
Other materials pertaining to nuclear science and engineering can be found in the Barton C. and Sally L. Hacker Nuclear Affairs Collection (MSS Hacker), Barton C. Hacker Papers (MSS HackerB), Charter Heslep Papers (MSS Heslep), Leonard M. Maki Nuclear Power Collection (MSS Maki), Ava Helen and Linus Pauling Papers (MSS Pauling), John C. Ringle Papers (MSS Ringle), E. Dale Trout Papers (MSS Trout), Chih H. Wang Papers (MSS Wang), Radiation Center Records (RG 202), and the History of Atomic Energy Collection (RB Energy).
In 2002, the Atomic Heritage Foundation conducted an oral history interview with Rockwell. A transcript and footage from the interview can be found on the Voices of the Manhattan Project site.
Backster, Cleve.; Gehman, Anne, 1936-; Panoff, Robert Michael.; Rickover, Hyman George.; Klingbeil, Bruce.; Klingbeil, John.; Mandil, Isaac Harry.; Muckerheide, James.; Wegner, William.
American Nuclear Society.; Oak Ridge National Laboratory.; Oak Ridge Y-12 Plant.; Manhattan Project (U.S.); Parapsychological Association.; Spindrift, Inc.; United States. Navy.; MPR Associates (Washington D.C.); National Institute for Discovery Science.; Radiation, Science, and Health, Inc.
Antinuclear movement.; Extrasensory perception.; Hormesis.; Nuclear energy--Environmental aspects--United States.; Nuclear energy--Law and legislation--United States.; Nuclear industry.; Nuclear propulsion.; Nuclear reactors--Shielding (Radiation); Nuclear reactors--United States--Safety measures.; Parapsychology.; Psychokinesis.; Radioactive waste disposal.; Radiation--Safety measures.; Spiritual healing.; Unidentified flying objects.
Audiocassettes.; Compact discs.; Floppy disks.; Microfiche.; Photographic prints.
Business and Corporations; Civil Procedure and Courts; Energy Production; Environmental Activism; Land Use; Laws and Legislation; Medicine and Health; Military; Nuclear Weapons and Testing; Religion; Science; Ships and Shipping; Artifacts; Electronic Records; Moving Images; Photographs; Sound Recordings
- Correspondence, 1966-2011; Series I
  Series I is composed of correspondence to and from Ted Rockwell and spans his career at MPR Associates, Inc. through his retirement. This series is largely comprised of correspondence relating to Rockwell's two primary interests--nuclear power and parapsychology. Correspondents include friends, family, colleagues, journalists, policymakers, organizational representatives, and fellow parapsychology enthusiasts. Of particular note is correspondence with Jim Muckerheide (RSH, Inc. co-founder), William Wegner (Naval Reactors alum and colleague), and Teed Rockwell (son and coauthor). Subjects include Admiral Rickover and the development of the United States' nuclear navy, nuclear power and energy production in the United States and abroad, developments in parapsychology research, and Rockwell's participation in nuclear energy and parapsychology organizations and initiatives such as the American Nuclear Society, the Naval Reactors alumni group, the Parapsychological Association, and the National Institute for Discovery Science.
  The series also includes materials relating to Rockwell's book and article publishing efforts consisting of correspondence with the U.S. Naval Institute Press and iUniverse, publisher solicitations, draft reviews, reader inquiries, and marketing and sales information.
  - Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 1.1)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 1.2)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 1.3)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1977 (Box-folder 1.4)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1977 (Box-folder 1.5)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1978 (Box-folder 1.6)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box-folder 1.7)
  - Correspondence, January-July 1979 (Box-folder 2.1)
  - Correspondence, August-December 1979 (Box-folder 2.2)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1980 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1980 (Box-folder 2.4)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1981 (Box-folder 2.5)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1981 (Box-folder 3.1)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box-folder 3.2)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1983 (Box-folder 3.3)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1983 (Box-folder 3.4)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box-folder 3.5)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 3.6)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box-folder 4.1)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 4.2)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 4.3)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box-folder 4.4)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box-folder 4.5)
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box-folder 4.6)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box-folder 4.7)
  - Correspondence, 1997 (Box-folder 4.8)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box-folder 4.9)
  - Correspondence, 1999 (Box-folder 5.1)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box-folder 5.2)
  - Correspondence, January-June 2001 (Box-folder 5.3)
  - Correspondence, July-December 2001 (Box-folder 5.4)
  - Correspondence, 2002 (Box-folder 5.5)
  - Correspondence, 2003 (Box-folder 5.6)
  - Correspondence, 2004 (Box-folder 6.1)
  - Correspondence, 2005 (Box-folder 6.2)
  - Correspondence, 2006 (Box-folder 6.3)
  - Correspondence, 2009 (Box-folder 6.4)
  - Correspondence, 2010 (Box-folder 6.5)
  - Correspondence, 2011 (Box-folder 6.6)
- Biographical Records & Published Materials, 1931-2010; Series II
  Series II is comprised of materials documenting Rockwell's personal life. Included are biographical sketches and transcripts from two oral history interviews with Rockwell; coursework and materials from his primary school education, New Trier High School, and Princeton University; fifteen notebooks generated by Rockwell containing to-do lists, contact information, and records of day-to-day activities; a series of essays on literature and writing collected by Rockwell; and an assortment of ephemera including two journal entries and a small "Victoria Para la Democracia" leaflet documenting his 1947 trip to Havana, Cuba, a ticket stub from the 1961 U.S presidential inauguration, a ticket stub from a 1961 dinner honoring Republican Congressional members, a series of souvenir letters from the Dionne Quintuplets, and a photocopied collection of sensational newspaper headlines featuring individuals with the Rockwell surname.
  The series also includes materials written by Rockwell for publication in the New Trier News, Winnetka Talk, and the Princeton Sunday News; an article entitled "Bred for Fury", on cockfighting published in True Magazine; and drafts, correspondence, research materials, and promotional items from several other books and articles authored by Rockwell including The Virtual Librarian, a mystery novel pitting a group of psychics against sentient library software, Us vs. Them, an exploration of conflict in modern society, and Vice Versa, a trilogy of one-act plays.
  - Articles and Newsclippings, 1942-1993 (Box-folder 6.7)
  - Class Reunions, 1997-2000 (Box-folder 6.8)
  - Disaster Plan, 1999-2008 (Box-folder 6.9)
  - Early Education, 1931-1939 (Box-folder 6.10)
  - Ephemera, 1943-1961 (Box-folder 7.1)
  - Essays, circa 1957-1964 (Box-folder 7.2)
  - Notebooks 1-4, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 7.3)
  - Notebooks 5-8, 1994-2000 (Box-folder 7.4)
  - Notebooks 9-12, 2000-2006 (Box-folder 7.5)
  - Notebooks 13-15, 2006-2010 (Box-folder 7.6)
  - Personal and Organizational Contact Information, circa 1980-2009 (Box-folder 7.7)
  - Princeton University Course Materials, 1933-1943 (Box-folder 7.8)
  - Princeton University Coursework, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 8.1)
  - Princeton University Coursework: "The Laboratory Development for the Manufacture of a Lightfast Lead Chromate Pigment", 1942 (Box-folder 8.2)
  - Princeton University Coursework: "Hard Rubber Reclamation by Catalytic Removal of Sulphur with Hydrogen", 1943 (Box-folder 8.3)
  - Princeton University Coursework: "Design of an Ethylene Plant", 1944 (Box-folder 8.4)
  - Princeton University Coursework: Nuclear Physics, 1944 (Box-folder 8.5)
  - Princeton University Coursework: "A Descriptive and a Mathematical Analysis of the Subject of Automatic Control and Instrumentation", 1945 (Box-folder 8.6)
  - Princeton University War Research: "Rubber Reserve Company Monomer Recovery Project", 1944 (Box-folder 8.7)
  - Princeton University, The Princeton Engineer, 1943-1990 (Box-folder 8.8)
  - Resumes and Biographical Sketches, circa 1976-2000 (Box-folder 8.9)
  - Rockwell Biographical Sketches, 1959-2010 (Box-folder 8.10)
  - Rockwell Book Reviews, 1978-1993 (Box-folder 8.11)
  - Rockwell Oral History Interview Transcript, 1996 (Box-folder 9.1)
  - Rockwell Oral History Interview Transcript, 2007 (Box-folder 9.2)
  - Rockwell Publication Clippings, 1939-1987 (Box-folder 9.3)
  - Rockwell Publications: New Trier High School, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 9.4)
  - Rockwell Publications: Princeton University, 1940 (Box-folder 9.5)
  - Rockwell Publications, 1968-2004 (Box-folder 9.6)
  - Rockwell Publication: "The 100th Monkey Effect", 1977-1979 (Box-folder 9.7)
  - Rockwell Publication: "Background", circa 2003 (Box-folder 9.8)
  - Rockwell Publication: Us vs. Them Correspondence, 1981-1989 (Box-folder 9.9)
  - Rockwell Publication: Us vs. Them Drafts, 1983 (Box-folder 9.10)
  - Rockwell Publication: Us vs. Them Drafts, 1985 (Box-folder 9.11)
  - Rockwell Publication: Us vs. Them Drafts, 1985 (Box-folder 10.1)
  - Rockwell Publication: Us. vs. Them Research Materials, 1950-1989 (Box-folder 10.2)
  - Rockwell Publication: Vice Versa: Three One Act Plays, 1990 (Box-folder 10.3)
  - Rockwell Publication: The Virtual Librarian, 1995-2009 (Box-folder 10.4)
  - Rockwell Publication: The Virtual Librarian Publication and Promotional Materials, 2007-2009 (Box-folder 10.5)
  - Rockwell Publication: The Virtual Librarian Research Materials, 1992-2007 (Box-folder 10.6)
  - Rockwell Publication: Winnetka Talk Cover Photo, 1939 (Box 84)
  - Skiing, circa 1977-1985 (Box-folder 11.1)
  - Tri-State College Honorary Doctorate, 1960 (Box-folder 11.2)
  - University of Virginia Student Problem Contest, 1943 (Box-folder 11.3)
  - Wisdom Hall of Fame, Wisdom Award of Honor, 1999 (Box-folder 11.4)
- Early Development of Nuclear Energy, 1940-2011; Series III
  Series III includes correspondence, design documents, and reference materials from the Oak Ridge National Laboratory (ORNL) in Oak Ridge, Tennessee where Rockwell worked as a process improvement engineer and a radiation shielding engineer between 1943 and 1949. Of particular note is a series of correspondence from Rockwell to his parents documenting his life and work from 1940-1946 at Princeton and ORNL, including observations of life at ORNL, descriptions of his day-to-day activities, and newsclippings and discussion of the significance of atomic energy following the bombings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki. The series also includes a file on security at ORNL; technical reports authored on Rockwell's work in radiation shielding; documentation from the Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology, including a mock diploma granting a "Doctor[ate] of Nuclear Husbandry"; an article by Rockwell entitled "Frontier Life Among the Atom Splitters" that appeared in a December 1945 issue of The Saturday Evening Post; and drafts of "Putting Wings on the Atom," a later article discussing nuclear-powered aircraft. Also included are materials from the Association of Scientists for Atomic Education and the Association of Oak Ridge Engineers and Scientists documenting efforts to place the United States' atomic energy program under civilian control. The series also contains several images of housing and work at Oak Ridge during and after the war years in both print and photocopy format.
  This series also contains extensive informational and promotional materials documenting the role of the Manhattan Project in ending World War II and includes materials from Rockwell's book Creating the New World, records of Oak Ridge's 50th Anniversary Celebration in 1992, issues of the Oak Ridge National Laboratory Review, and materials from the Atomic Heritage Foundation, the Manhattan Project Heritage Preservation Association, the National Atomic Museum, and the National Museum of Nuclear Science and History, and a file on former ORNL Director Clarence Edward Larson.
  - Association of Scientists for Atomic Education / Association of Oak Ridge Engineers and Scientists, 1946-1974 (Box-folder 11.5)
  - Atomic Heritage Foundation, 2002-2011 (Box-folder 11.6)
  - Atomic Heritage Foundation, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 11.7)
  - Correspondence (Binder I), 1940-1945 (Box-folder 11.8)
  - Correspondence (Binder II), 1945-1947 (Box-folder 12.1)
  - Correspondence, 2003-2010 (Box-folder 12.2)
  - Larson, Clarence Edward, 1996-2003 (Box-folder 12.3)
  - Manhattan Project Heritage Preservation Association, Inc., 2003-2006 (Box-folder 12.4)
  - Manhattan Project Informational and Promotional Materials, 1991-2008 (Box-folder 12.5)
  - Manhattan Project Informational and Promotional Materials, circa 2000-2010 (Box-folder 12.6)
  - National Atomic Museum, 2008-2009 (Box-folder 12.7)
  - National Museum of Nuclear Science and History, 2009 (Box-folder 12.8)
  - Newsclippings, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 12.9)
  - Oak Ridge 50th Anniversary Celebration, 1992 (Box-folder 12.10)
  - Oak Ridge National Laboratory Review, 1976-2001 (Box-folder 13.1)
  - Oak Ridge Raw Materials Purchasing, 1947 (Box-folder 13.2)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology, 1946-1953 (Box-folder 13.3)
  - Oak Ridge School of Reactor Technology "Doctor of Neutron Husbandry" Certificate, 1953 (Box 84)
  - Photographs of Oak Ridge, circa 1945-1980 (Box-folder 13.4)
  - Rockwell Publication: Creating the New World, 2001-2010 (Box-folder 13.5)
  - Rockwell Publication: Creating the New World, 2001-2011 (Box-folder 13.6)
  - Rockwell Publication: "Frontier Life Among the Atom Splitters," The Saturday Evening Post, 1945 (Box-folder 13.7)
  - Rockwell Publication: "Putting Wings on the Atom", 1947-1948 (Box-folder 13.8)
  - Rockwell Technical Reports, 1946-1950 (Box-folder 14.1)
  - Rockwell Technical Reports, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 14.2)
  - Security at Oak Ridge, 1945-1949 (Box-folder 14.3)
- U.S Navy, 1949-2012; Series IV